# Vincent O'Leary

☑ vincent@f-m.fm

vincentoleary.com

in linkedin.com/in/vjoleary

#### Personal Statement

Seeking a position at the expiration of my term with Americorps that will allow me to maximize my 10+ years of experience in science communication and mentoring in order to connect environmental policy and research with the communities and people they affect.

## Professional History

Sep 2018 - Sep 2019 Americorps VISTA (Jon Doctorick)

Center for STEM Education and Career Development, Carnegie Science Center, Pittsburgh, PA

• Developing a guide for mentor programming at the Carnegie Science Center Fab Lab that documents best practices, workflows, and examples that other institutions will be able to use as guidelines in creating similar mentoring programs

Jun - Jul 2018 Truman Scholarship Summer Institute Intern (Reid Sherman, PhD.)

U.S. Global Change Research Program, White House Office of Science and Technology Policy, Washington, DC

• Recognized for exemplary efforts towards the release of Volume II of the Fourth National Climate Assessment, a nonpartisan government effort to identify and explain the risks of climate change

Jun - Aug 2017 **NOAA Hollings Scholar Intern** (Chris Amante, PhD.) National Centers for Environmental Information (NCEI), NOAA, Boulder, CO.

• Developed a global model of elevation with public bathymetric and topographic datasets using ArcGIS, to be made available as the first update to NOAA's standard ETOPO1 model in 10 years

Mar - Sep 2016 Biodiversity Informatics Research CO-OP (Steve Dilliplane)
Center for Systematic Biology and Evolution, Academy of Natural Sciences (ANSP), Philadelphia, PA

• Created an automated work-flow using MySQL to import and standardize several distinct Symbiota, Microsoft Excel, and FileMaker Pro databases into Specify repository, allowed for data to be searched museum wide

Dec 2013 - Dec 2017 Curatorial Assistant (Ted Daeschler, PhD.) Vertebrate Paleontology Collection, Academy of Natural Sciences (ANSP), Philadelphia, PA

• Migrated 8800+ handwritten records into a FileMaker Pro database and created a workflow to normalize data to be shared online for the first time

## Teaching and Outreach

2018 English for Speakers of Other Languages Instructor St. Thomas Aquinas Catholic Community Center, Philadelphia, PA

• Led small group discussion with 15+ adults for 2 hours per week during English Language instruction

2017 - 2018 **High School STEM Mentor** Gaining Early Awareness and Readiness for Undergraduate Programs (GEAR UP), Philadelphia, PA

• Mentored 50+ students in 9th and 10th grade science classrooms for 8 hours per week

2016 - 2017 Drexel Community Scholar for After-school Learning

Lindy Center for Civic Engagement, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA

• Coordinated after-school STEM activities for 30+ students in 3rd and 4th grade for 5 hours per week

#### Education

2013 - 2018 **Drexel University**, Pennoni Honors College, Philadelphia, PA GPA - 3.5 **B.S. Environmental Science**, minor in Geoscience

Continuing education and certificates

- Nonprofit Board Prep Program, Young Involved Philadelphia (YIP), Philadelphia, PA (2018)
- Rebuilding Native Nations, Native Nations Institute at University of Arizona, Tuscon, AZ (2017)

## Relevant Skills

Education and Communication - Public speaking, Verbal and written communication, Event planning, Curriculum development, Childhood education in formal and informal environments, Classroom management, Technical presentations, Building stakeholder engagement

Computer - ArcGIS, GDAL/OGR, QGIS, Python, R, OpenRefine, SQL, FileMaker Pro, Git/GitHub, Microsoft Office Suite (Word, Excel, PowerPoint), Outlook email, Markdown (this resume is written in Markdown), HTML, LaTeX, Bash and shell scripting

Field and Lab - Managing lab notebooks, Titration, Filtration, RTK/PPK and laser level surveying, Open channel hydraulic surveys, Backpack electrofishing, Radio-telemetry, Scanning electron (SEM) and petrographic microscopy

### Recent Awards and Grants

- 2017 Harry S. Truman Scholarship
- 2017 Morris K. and Stewart L. Udall Scholarship
- 2017 Society for Science and the Public Advocacy Grant (\$3,000)
- 2017 Drexel University Arcadia Grant (\$3,000)
- 2016 National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Ernest F. Hollings Scholarship
- 2016 Drexel University ExCITe Center Seed Fund Research Grant (\$5,000)
- 2016 Drexel University Steinbright Corporate Partners Grant (\$4,000)

### Recent Publications

- 3 Amante, C., V. O'Leary (TBD), GLOBATO: An enhanced global relief model at 30 arc-seconds resolution. Report in preparation for publication by NOAA.
- 2 Seltmann, K., S. Lafia, D. Paul, S. James, D. Bloom, N. Rios, S. Ellis, U. Farrell, J. Utrup, M. Yost, E. Davis, R. Emery, G. Motz, J. Kimmig, V. Shirey, E. Sandall, D. Park, C. Tyrrell, R. Thackurdeen, M. Collins, V. O'Leary, H. Prestridge, C. Evelyn, B. Nyberg (2018), Georeferencing for Research Use (GRU): An integrated geospatial training paradigm for biocollections researchers and data providers. Research Ideas and Outcomes 4: e32449.
- 1 (*Staff contributor*) USGCRP, 2018: Impacts, Risks, and Adaptation in the United States: Fourth National Climate Assessment, Volume II [Reidmiller, D.R., C.W. Avery, D.R. Easterling, K.E. Kunkel, K.L.M. Lewis, T.K. Maycock, and B.C. Stewart (eds.)]. U.S. Global Change Research Program, Washington, DC, USA, 1515 pp.

### **Selected Presentations**

- 3 Shirey, V., V. O'Leary, S. Dilliplane (2017), More Than a Map: Adventures in Biodiversity Informatics Visualization. Presented at 2017 Annual Meeting, SPNHC, Denver, CO, 18-24, Jun.
- 2 **O'Leary, V** (2017), Building Communities around a Shared River. Presented at Week of Undergraduate Excellence, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA, 1-5 May.
- 1 **O'Leary**, **V** (2017), From Online to On the River: Opportunities for Data Storytelling. Presented at River Research Seminar, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, 28 Apr.